Arijit Kumar Roy

arijitroy003@gmail.com | +917980045423 | Bangalore, India | Github | LinkedIn

PROFILE SUMMARY

I am a seasoned Software Engineer with 6+ years of cumulative experience in Data and AI Engineering, Linux, Distributed Systems, Cloud (AWS/Azure) and SaaS products. Currently working in a Data Platform Engineering role with previous experience in Full Stack Development (MEAN/MERN). I have worked with technologies in Conversational AI, Applied Generative AI, Lang chain, Embeddings, Python, Golang, Spark, Databricks, Snowflake, dbt, Rest APIs, DeltaLake, and Databases regularly looking over the CI/CD and production deployment and deliverables in my team.

EXPERIENCE

RED HAT | SENIOR SOFTWARE ENGINEER | DATA & AI, PLATFORM ENGINEERING Apr 2024 - Present | Bengaluru, India

- Building a self-service Data Platform Framework, with the dream to open-source it
- Tech: Git Ops, Snowflake, dbt-Core, AWS, Golang, Kubernetes, Python, Fivetran, Atlan, CI/CD
- Delving into the world of inner-source, contribution model, data transparency driven system design
- Onboarded and integrated Atlan, data governance SaaS, shipped to production, scale growth & adoption
- Building Metadata Completeness for Agentic frameworks, MCP servers, AI observability & tools

BEEM | SR. DATA ENGINEER | FINANCIAL SERVICES

Nov 2023 - Mar 2024 | Remote, US

- Al First Fintech Startup for US working class consumers
- Developing Data & Al Platform (50M+ users) for Personal Finance Management tools using LLMs | Data Governance and Orchestration
- Investor pitches & completed fundraising from Databricks of \$16k, with future commitments of \$24k
- Created workflows to analyse clickstream data of users (AWS, Python, Databricks, Mixpanel, Metabase)

TATA DIGITAL | Sr. Software Engineer | E-commerce, Retail

Aug 2021 – Oct 2023 | Strategic Initiatives | Bengaluru, IN

- Conversational Al | Big Data | Data Warehousing (120M+ users)
- Working on Generative AI based Product Search Tool and Recommendation Engine using Azure Open AI, Mistal, Lang Chain, Embeddings, Vector Databases (Chroma / Milvus)
- Developed <u>Delta Lake Architecture</u> and optimized TCO (Python, Spark, Databricks, Delta, ADLS, CI/CD in Azure DevOps, KQL/SQL)
- Implemented Load balancing to reduce operation TTL by 10 times
- Reduced operation latency by 75%, cost by 80%
- Customer Support Call Evaluation using Deep learning, Speech-to-Text, Audio ML techniques
- Created micro-services for API monitoring for multiple brands integrations & downtime alerts for the **AI chatbot** program, for 12 indic languages
- Live Dashboards for 24x7 for real-time monitoring

GNOSIS LAB | SOFTWARE DEVELOPER, FOUNDING ENGINEER | NASSCOM 10K STARTUPS June 2019 - May 2021 | Kolkata, IN

- Built an Al bot for a SaaS Platform to automate social media marketing on Instagram, Twitter using Serverless, Python, AWS, Web Scraping, Data Modeling
- MEAN Stack Developer (Typescript, Angular, AWS, Lambda, DynamoDB, MongoDB, Docker)
- Worked on Learning Management System Platform, backend heavy (50+ APIs)

PROJECTS

DOCTOR - CLINICAL MANAGEMENT SOFTWARE | FREELANCE PROJECT

2021 | React Native, Google Cloud, Firebase, Razorpay

- Delivered production ready android app and website for appointment bookings and doctor practice management using React Native and Firebase as a backend.
- Integrating Razorpay for payment services for customers to securely transact.

OFFLINE FILE SYSTEM SEARCH | RESEARCH

PROJECT | SUMMER SCHOOL

March 2017 | Python, Linux Bash tools, NLP

 Document Indexer for Information Retrieval under supervision of <u>Dr. Dwaipayan Roy</u>, Information Retrieval Lab, <u>Indian Statistical Institute</u>, Kolkata

EDUCATION

JADAVPUR UNIVERSITY

MASTERS IN COMPUTER APPLICATIONS Aug 2018 - Jun 2021 | Kolkata, IN Distributed Systems / Cloud Computing Cum. GPA: 8.81 / 10.0

RAMAKRISHNA MISSION VIDYAMANDIRA

BS IN COMPUTER SCIENCE Aug 2015 - May 2018 | Howrah, IN Cum. GPA: 8.49 / 10.0

SOUTH POINT HIGH SCHOOL

HIGH SCHOOL Grad. 2015 | Kolkata, India Grade: A+

SKILLS

PROGRAMMING

Core Technologies:

Python • Databricks • Snowflake
DeltaLake • Pyspark • AWS
Git Ops • Kubernetes • LangChain
OpenAl / Claude / Mistral • LLMs • Javascript
Additional:

Typescript • Git • Azure
SQL/NoSQL • NodeJS • APIs
MVC • Serverless • Docker
Azure DevOps • React Native
Dbt • Golang • Ansible
Engineering Data Management • Governance
SSO/OAuth systems • Cursor • Claude Code

SPECIALIZATION

Distributed Systems • Information Retrieval Electronics • Cloud Computing Data Structures Algorithms
Operating Systems
Object Oriented Programming
ML/AI • NLP

LANGUAGES

English • Bengali • Hindi

HOBBIES

Chess • Table Tennis
Tech blogging • Linux Ricing

LINKS

Github:// arijitroy003 LinkedIn:// Arijit Roy